14 at 9:00 the next morning his servant came in with a cup of chocolate on a
tray and opened the shutters. Dorian was sleeping quite peacefully, lying on his
right side, with one hand underneath his cheek. He looked like a boy who had been
tired out with play, or study. The man had to touch him twice on
the shoulder before he woke, and as he opened his eyes a faint smile passed
across his lips, as though he had been lost in some delightful dream. Yet he had
not dreamed at all. His night had been untroubled by any images of pleasure or
of pain. But youth smiles without any reason. It is one of its chiefest
charms. He turned round, and leaning upon his elbow, began to sip his
chocolate. The mellow November sun came streaming into the room. The sky was was
bright, and there was a genial warmth in the air. It was almost like a morning in
May. Gradually the events of the preceding night crept with silent
bloodstained feet into his brain and reconstructed themselves there with terrible
distinctness. He winced at the memory of all that he had suffered, and for a
moment the same curious feeling of loathing for Basil hallwood that had
made him kill him as he sat in the chair
came back back to him, and he grew cold with passion. The dead man was still sitting
there, too, and in the sunlight now. How horrible that was! Such hideous things
were for the darkness, not for the day. He felt that if he brooded on what
he had gone through he would sicken or grow mad. There were sins whose fascination
was more in the memory than in the doing of them, strange triumphs that gratified
the pride more than the passions, and gave to the intellect a quickened sense
of joy, greater than any joy they brought, or could ever bring, to the
senses. But this was not one of them. It
was a thing to be driven out of the mind, to be drugged with poppies, to be
strangled lest it might strangle one itself. When the half hour struck, he
passed his hand across his forehead, and then got up hastily and dressed himself
with even more than than his usual care, giving a good deal of attention to the
choice of his neck tie and scarf pin and changing his rings more than once. He
spent a long time also over breakfast, tasting the various dishes, talking to
his valet about some new liveries that he was thinking of getting made for the
servants at Selby, and going through his correspondence. At some of the letters, he
smiled. Three of them bored him. One he read several times over and then tore up
with a slight look of annoyance in his face.
“That awful thing, a woman’s memory!” as Lord Henry had once said. After he had
drunk his cup of black coffee, he wiped his lips slowly with a napkin, motioned
to his servant to wait, and going over to the table, sat down and wrote two letters.
One he put in his pocket, the other he handed to the
valet. “Take this round to 152 Hartford Street, Francis, and if Mr. Campbell is out
of town, get his address.” As soon as he was alone, he lit a
cigarette and began sketching upon a piece of paper, drawing first flowers and bits of
architecture, and then human faces. Suddenly he remarked that every
face that he drew seemed to have a fantastic likeness to Basil
hallwood He frowned, and getting up, went over to the bookcase and took out a volume at
hazard. He was determined that he would not think about what had happened until
until it became absolutely necessary that he should do so. When he had stretched himself on the
sofa, he looked at the title page of the book. It was Go's emo aame Sharon's
Japanese paper edition, with the jacmart etching. The binding was of Citron green
leather, with a design of guilt trellis work and dotted pomegranates. It had been
given to him by Adrien Singleton. As he turned over the pages
his his eye fell on the poem about the hand of lassaire the cold yellow hand D anoral
LA with its downy red hairs and its dxa phone He glanced at his own white taper
fingers, shuddering slightly in spite of himself, and passed on, till he came to
those lovely stanzas upon Venice surun neam chroma laen
devad esal How exquisite they were! As one read them, one seemed to be
floating down the green waterways of the pink and pear city, seated in a black
gondola with silver prow and trailing curtains. The mere lines looked to him
like those straight lines of turquoise blue that follow one as one pushes out to the
Lio The sudden flashes of color reminded him of the gleam of the opal and Iris
throated birds that flutter around the tall honeycombed campan or stalk, with
such stately grace, through the dim dust stained arcades. Leaning back with half
closed eyes, he kept saying over and over to himself Deon unad rose Su marra dun
escaler The whole of Venice was in those two lines. He remembered the autumn that he
had passed there, and a wonderful love that had stirred him to mad delightful
folies There was romance in every place.
But Venice, like Oxford, had kept the background for romance, and, to the true
romantic, background was everything, or almost everything. Basil had been with him part
of the time, and had gone wild over tinay Poor Basil! What a horrible way for
a man to die! He sighed, and took up the volume again, and tried to
forget. He read of the swallows that fly in and out of the little cafe at Smyrna
where the hajis sit counting their amber beads and the turbaned merchants smoked
their long tassled pipes and talk gravely to each other; he read of the
Obelisk in the plasta Concord that weeps tears of granite in its lonely sunless
exile and longs to be back by the hot Lotus covered Nile, where there are
Sphinxes, and Rose Red EES and white vultures with gilded claws, and
crocodiles with small Barrel eyes that crawl over the green steaming mud; he
began to brood over those verses which, drawing music from Kiss stained marble,
tell of that curious statue that goer compares to a contralto voice, the
monster charmant that couches in the poery room of the
Lou But after a time the book fell from his hand. He grew nervous, and a horrible
fit of terror came over him. What if Alan Campbell should be out of
England? Days would elapse before he could come back. Perhaps he might refuse
to come. What could he do then? Every moment was of vital
importance. They had been great friends once 5 years before— —almost inseparable,
indeed. Then the intimacy had come suddenly to an end. When they met in
society now, it was only Dorian Gray who smiled: Alan Campbell never
did. He was an extremely clever young man, though he had no real appreciation of
the visible arts, and whatever little sense of the beauty of poetry he
possessed he had gained entirely from Dorian. His dominant intellectual passion was for science.
At Cambridge he had spent a great deal of his time working in the laboratory,
and had taken a good class in the Natural Science treos of his year. Indeed,
he was still devoted to the study of chemistry, and had a laboratory of his
own in which he used to shut himself up all day long, greatly to the annoyance of
his mother, who had set her heart on his standing for Parliament and had a vague
idea that a chemist was a person who made up prescriptions. He was an
excellent musician, however, as well, and played both the violin and the piano better than most
amateurs. In fact, it was music that had first brought him and Dorian Gray
together— —music and that indefinable attraction that Dorian seemed to be able
to exercise whenever he wished— —and, indeed, exercised often without being
conscious of it. They had met at Lady Burkes the night that Rubenstein played
there, and after that used to be always seen together at the opera and wherever
good music was going on. For 18 months their intimacy lasted. Campbell was
always either at Selby Royal or in groer Square. To him, as to many others, Dorian
Gray was the type of everything that is wonderful and fascinating in
life. Whether or not a quarrel had taken place between them no one ever knew. But
suddenly people remarked that they scarcely spoke when they met and that
Campbell seemed always to go away early from any party at which Dorian Gray was present.
He had changed, too— —was strangely melancholy at times, appeared almost to
dislike hearing music, and would never himself play, giving as his excuse, when
he was called upon, that he was so absorbed in science that he had no time
left in which to practice And this was certainly true. Every day he seemed to
become more interested in biology, and his name appeared once or twice in some
of the scientific reviews in connection with certain curious experiments.
This was the man Dorian Gray was waiting for. Every second he kept glancing at the
clock. As the minutes went by he became horribly agitated. At last he got up and
began to pace up and down the room, looking like a beautiful caged thing. He
took long stealthy strides. His hands were curiously cold. The suspense became
unbearable. Time seemed to him to be crawling with feet of lead, while he by
monstrous winds was being swept towards the jagged edge of some black Clift of
precipice. He knew what was waiting for him there; saw it, indeed, and, shuddering,
crushed with dank hands his burning lids as though he would have robbed the very
brain of sight and driven the eyeballs back into their cave. It was useless. The brain had its
own food on which it battened, and the imagination, made grotesque by terror,
twisted and distorted as a living thing by by pain, danced like some foul puppet
on a stand and grinned through moving masks. Then, suddenly, time stopped for him.
Yes: that blind slow breathing thing crawled no more, and horrible thoughts,
time being dead, raced nimbly on in front, and dragged a hideous future from its
grave, and showed it to him. He stared at it. Its very horror made him
stone. At last the door opened and his servant entered. He turned glazed eyes upon
him and Mr. Campbell, sir,” said the man. A sigh of relief broke from his parched
lips, and the color came back to his cheeks. “Ask him to come in at once,
Francis.” He felt that he was himself again. His mood of cowardice had passed
away. The man bowed and retired. In a few moments, Alan Campbell walked in, looking
very stern and rather pale, his palor being intensified by his cold black hair
and dark eyebrows Allan This is kind of you. I thank you for
coming I'd intended never to enter your house again, Gray. But you said it was a matter of
life and death.” His voice was hard and cold. He spoke with slow
deliberation. There was a look of contempt in the steady searching gaze
that he turned on Dorian. He kept his hands in the pockets of his asrian coat,
and seemed not to have noticed the gesture with which he had been greeted.
“Yes: it is a matter of life and death, Alan, and to more than one person. Sit
down.” Campbell took a chair by the table, and Dorian sat opposite to him. The two
men’s eyes met. In Dorian’s there was infinite pity. He knew that what he was
going to do was dreadful. After a strained moment of silence, he leaned across and said, very
quietly, but watching the effect of each word upon the face of him he had sent
for Allan in a locked room at the top of this house, a room to which nobody but
myself has access, a dead man is seated at a table he's been dead 10 hours now.
Don’t stir, and don’t look at me like
that. Who the man is, why he died, how he died, are matters that do not concern you.
What you have to do is this—” “Stop, Gray. I don’t want to know anything further.
Whether what you have told me is true or not true doesn’t concern me. I entirely
declined to be mixed up in your life.
Keep your horrible secrets to yourself.
They don’t interest me anymore Allan they will have to interest
you. This one will have to interest you I'm awfully sorry for you, Alan. But I
can’t help myself. You are the one man who is able to save me I'm forced to
bring you into the matter. I have no option.
Alan, you are scientific. You know about chemistry and things of that kind. You
have made experiments. What you have got to do is to destroy the thing that is
upstairs— —to destroy it so that not a vestage of it will be left. Nobody saw
this person come into the house. Indeed, at the present moment he's supposed to
be in Paris. He will not be missed for months. When he's missed, there must be no
trace of him found here. You Allan you must change him, and everything that
belongs to him, into a handful of ashes that I may scatter in the
air.” “You are mad, Dorian.” “Ah! I was waiting for you to call me
Dorian.” “You are mad, I tell you— —mad to imagine that I would raise a finger to
help you, mad to make this monstrous confession. I will have nothing to do
with this matter, whatever it is. Do you think I'm going to peril my reputation
for you what What is it to me what devil’s work you are up
to?” “It was suicide, Alan I'm glad of that.
But who drove him to it? You, I should fancy.” “Do you still refuse to do this for
me?” “Of course I refuse. I will have absolutely nothing to do with it. I don’t
care what shame comes on you. You deserve it all. I should not be sorry to see you
disgraced, publicly disgraced. How dare you ask me, of all men men in the world,
to mix myself up in this horror? I should have thought you knew more about
people’s characters. Your friend Lord Henry Waton can’t have taught you much
about psychology, whatever else he has taught you. Nothing will induce me to
stir a step to help you. You have come to
the wrong man. Go to some of your friends.
Don’t come to me Allan it was murder. I killed him. You don’t know what
he had made me suffer. Whatever my life is, he had more
to do with the making or the marring of it than poor Harry has had. He may not
have intended it, the result was the same.” “Murder! Good God, Dorian, is that what you
have come to? I shall not inform upon you. It is not my business. Besides, without my stirring
in the matter, you are certain to be arrested. Nobody ever commits a crime
without doing something stupid. But I will have nothing to do with
it.” “You must must have something to do with it. Wait, wait a moment; listen to me. Only
listen, Alan. All I ask of you is to perform a certain scientific experiment.
You go to hospitals and dead houses and the horrors that you do there don’t
affect you. If in some hideous dissecting room or feted laboratory you found this
man lying on a leaden table with red gutters scooped out in it for the blood
to flow through, you would simply look upon him as an admirable
subject. You would not turn a hair. You would not believe that you were doing
anything wrong. On the contrary, you would probably feel that you were benefiting
the human race, or increasing the sum of knowledge in the world, or gratifying
intellectual curiosity, or something of that kind. What I want you to do is merely
what you have often done before. Indeed, to destroy a body must be far less
horrible than what you're accustomed to work at. And, remember,
it is the only piece of evidence against me. If it is discovered, I am lost; and it
is sure to be discovered unless you help me.” “I have no desire to help you. You
forget that I'm simply indifferent to the whole thing. It has nothing to do
with me Allan I entreat you. Think of the position I am in. Just before you came I
almost fainted with terror. You may know terror yourself someday No! don’t think
of that. Look at the matter purely from the scientific point of view. You don’t
inquire where the dead things on which you experiment come from. Don’t inquire
now. I have told you too much as it is.
But I beg of you to do this. We were friends once
Allan Don’t speak about those days, Dorian— —they are dead.” “The dead linger
sometimes. The man upstairs will not go away. He is sitting at the table with
bowed head and outstretched arms Allan Allan If you don’t come to my assistance,
I am ruined. Why, they will hang me Allan Don’t you understand? They will hang me
for what I have done.” “There is no good in prolonging this
scene. I absolutely refuse to do anything in the matter. It is insane of you to ask
me.” “You refuse?” “Yes.” “I entreat you, Alan.” “It is useless.”
The same look of pity came into Dorian Gray’s eyes. Then he stretched out his
hand, took a piece of paper, and wrote something on it. He read it over twice,
folded it carefully, and pushed it across the table. Having done this, he got up and
went over to the window. Campbell looked at him in surprise, and then took up the
paper, and opened it. As he read it, his face became ghastly pale and he fell
back in his chair. A horrible sense of sickness came over him. He felt as if his
heart was beating itself to death in some empty hollow. After 2 or 3 minutes
of terrible silence, Dorian turned around and Cay and stood behind him, putting his
hand upon his shoulder. “I am so sorry for you, Alan,” he murmured, “but you leave me no
alternative. I have a letter written already. Here it is. You see the address.
If you don’t help me, I must send it. If
you don’t help me, I will send it. You
know what the result will be. But you are going to help me. It is impossible for
you to refuse now. I tried to spare you.
You will do me the justice to admit that.
You were stern, harsh, offensive. You treated me as no man has ever dared to
treat me— —no living man, at any rate. I
bore it all. Now it is for me to dictate terms.” Campbell buried his face in his
hands, and a shudder passed through him.
“Yes, it is my turn to dictate terms, Alan.
You know what they are. The thing is quite simple. Come, don’t work yourself
into this fever. The thing has to be done.
Face it, and do it.” A groan broke from Campbell’s lips
and he shivered all over. The ticking of the clock on the mantlepiece seemed to
him to be dividing time into separate atoms of agony, each of which was too terrible to
be born He felt as if an iron ring was being slowly tightened around his forehead, as
if the disgrace with which he was threatened had already come upon him. The
hand upon his shoulder weighed like a hand of lead. It was intolerable. It seemed to crush
him. “Come, Alan, you must decide at once.” “I cannot do it,” he said, mechanically, as
though words could alter things. “You must.
You have no choice. Don’t delay.” He hesitated a moment. “Is there a fire in the room
upstairs?” “Yes, there is a gas fire with asbestos.” “I shall have to go home and get
some things from the laboratory.” “No, Alan, you must not leave
the house. Write out on a sheet of Note Paper what you want and my servant will
take a cab and bring the things back to you.” Campbell scrolled a few lines,
blotted them, and addressed an envelope to his assistant. Dorian took the note up
and read it carefully. Then he rang the bell and gave it to his valet, with
orders to return as soon as possible and to bring the things with him. As the hall
door shut, Campbell started nervously, and having got up from the chair, went over
to the chimney piece He was shivering with a kind of auu For nearly 20 minutes,
neither of the men spoke. A fly buzzed noisily about the room, and the ticking
of the clock was like the beat of a hammer. As the chime struck one C Umble
turned round, and looking at Dorian Gray, saw that his eyes were filled with
tears. There was something in the purity and refinement of that sad face that
seemed to enrage him. “You are infamous, absolutely infamous!” he muttered. “Hush
Allan You have saved my life,” said Dorian. “Your life? Good heavens! what a
life that is! You have gone from corruption to corruption, and now you
have culmin minated in crime. In doing what I am going to do— —what you force me
to do— —it is not of your life that I am thinking.” “Ah Allan murmured Dorian with a
sigh, “I wish you had a thousandth part of the pity for me that I have for
you.” He turned away as he spoke and stood looking out at the garden. Campbell made no
answer. After about 10 minutes a knock came to the door, and the servant entered,
carrying a large mahogany chest of chemicals, with a long coil of steel and
platinum wire and two rather curiously shaped iron clamps. “Shall I leave the things here, sir?”
he asked Campbell. “Yes,” said Dorian. “And I'm afraid, Francis, that I have another errand for
you. What is the name of the man at Richmond who supplies Selby with orchids?” “Harden,
sir.” “Yes— —Harden. You must go down to Richmond at once,
see Harden personally, and tell him to send twice as many orchids as I ordered,
and to have as few white ones as possible. In fact, I don’t want any white
ones. It is a lovely day, Francis, and Richmond is a very pretty place—
—otherwise I wouldn’t bother you about it.” “No trouble, sir. At what time shall I be
back?” Dorian looked at Campbell. “How long will your experiment take, Alan?” he said
in a calm indifferent voice. The the presence of a third person
in the room seemed to give him extraordinary courage. Campbell frowned and bit his
lip. “It will take about 5 hours,” he answered. “It will be time enough, then, if
you are back at halfast 7 Francis. Or stay: just leave my things out for
dressing. You can have the evening to yourself I'm not dining at home, so I shall not want
you.” “Thank you, sir,” said the man, leaving the room. “Now, Alan, there is not a moment to
be lost. How heavy this chest is! I’ll take it for you. You bring the other
things.” He spoke rapidly and in an authoritative manner. Campbell felt
dominated by him. They left the room together. When they reached the top
landing, Dorian took out the key and turned it in the lock. Then he stopped,
and a troubled look came into his eyes.
He shuddered. “I don’t think I can go in, Alan,”
he murmured. “It is nothing to me. I don’t require you,” said Campbell coldly. Dorian
half opened the door. As he did so, he saw the face of his portrait learing in the
sunlight. On the floor in front of it the torn curtain was lying. He remembered
that the night before he had forgotten, for the first time in his life, to hide
the fatal canvas, and was about to rush forward, when he drew back with a
shudder. What was that loathsome red Jew that gleamed, wet and glistening, on one
of the hands, as though the canvas had sweated blood? How horrible it was!— !—more
horrible, it seemed to him for the moment, than the silent thing that he knew was
stretched across the table, the thing whose grotesque misshapen shadow on the
spotted carpet showed him that it had not stirred, but was still there, as he
had left it. He heaved a deep breath, opened the door a little wider, and with
half closed eyes and a verted head, walked quickly in, determined that he
would not look even once upon the dead man. Then, stooping down and taking up the
golden purple hanging, he flung it right over the picture. There he stopped, feeling afraid
to turn round, and his eyes fixed themselves on the intricacies of the
pattern before him. He heard Campbell bringing in the heavy chest, and the
irons, and the other things that he had required for his dreadful work. He began
to wonder if he and Basil hallwood had ever met, and, if so, what they had thought
of each other. “Leave me now,” said a stern voice behind him. He turned and hurried
out, just conscious that the dead man had been thrust back into the chair and that
Campbell was gazing into a glistening yellow face. As he was going downstairs, he heard
the key being turned in the lock.
It was long after 7 when Campbell came back into the library. He was pale, but absolutely
calm. “I have done what you asked me to do,” he muttered. “And now
goodbye Let us never see each other again.” “You have saved me from ruin, Alan. I
cannot forget that,” said Dorian simply. As soon as Campbell had left, he went
upstairs. There was a horrible smell of nitric acid in the room. But the thing
that had been sitting at the table was gone. CHAPTER